Today's דף daf is קנז, kuf nun zayin, 157, נזק. nezek. So,
and we pick up at the bottom of קנו עמוד ב. kuf
nun vav amud bet. We had just read the משנה, mishna, but
let's read that again. So the משנה mishna says as follows: רבי
אליעזר אומר בשבת ועל פי קיימן. Rabbi Eliezer omer beshabbos ve'al pi
kayaman. So we had an opinion in the previous משנה. mishna. It
seems like it was רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that said that he
denied the whole idea of a שכיב מרע shchiv mera that his
verbal gift counts. And here we have it seems like the same
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer making a distinction between שבת Shabbos and the
weekday. So תוספות Tosafot says one it was רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar,
the other's רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. It's not the same opinion. The
רי"ף Rif seems to have them both as the same opinion, so
he's clarifying what he said before. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi has this as
the חכמים. chachamim. Anyway, regardless, here's an opinion that distinguishes and says
on שבת Shabbos we allow the verbal gift of a שכיב מרע
shchiv mera to work, מפני שאין יכול לכתוב. mipnei she'ein yachol lichtov.
He can't write it, and therefore the rabbis gave him that permission,
that made that a possibility, you know, going to the larger context
of לא תתרוש ביתיה lo tithrosh beiteih etc., we had to allow
it. There was no other option. אבל לא בחול, aval lo bechol,
in the weekday we didn't allow because he could write it down.
רבי יהושע אומר בשבת אמרו קל וחומר בחול. Rabbi Yehoshua omer beshabbos
amru kal vachomer bechol. Yes, they said it by שבת, Shabbos, but
from there we can derive an inference that it's certainly the case
in a weekday. You could say שבת Shabbos is a time when
no קניינים kinyanim are possible, and if we allow a קניין kinyan
to work on שבת Shabbos when no קניינים kinyanim are possible, certainly
in the week when a normal קניין kinyan is possible, this can
work as a type of a קניין. kinyan.
כיוצא בדבר, keyotzei badavar, similarly כיוצא בו, keyotzei bo, a similar type
of a debate of can you... they said something in one case,
do you assume it's only that case or it's even that case?
So זוכין לקטן ואין זוכין לגדול, zochin lekatan ve'ein zochin legadol, דברי
רבי אליעזר. divrei Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you can
take possession of something on behalf of a minor, but not on
behalf of an adult. Let the adult take possession for it himself.
So they only allowed it in the case of a קטן. katan.
רבי יהושע אומר לקטן אמרו קל וחומר לגדול. Rabbi Yehoshua omer lekatan
amru kal vachomer legadol. No, if you can do it for a
minor, so even who can't do it for himself, and how can
you do it for him if he can't do it for himself?
You're not an extension of him. But he himself can't do it.
So they allowed the case where it wasn't even possible, certainly they're
going to allow a case where for an adult who could do
it himself, it's easier then for you as doing it on his
behalf. Yes.
According to this, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer rejects the principle of זוכין
לאדם שלא בפניו? zochin leadam shelo befanav?
Correct, except in the case of a minor. I know, it's like
we consider it to be this like ironclad principle. The same way
we assume that דברי שכיב מרע ככתובים וכמסורים דמו divrei shchiv mera
kechtuvim uchemesurim damu is this ironclad principle. And he rejects it. I
mean, one interesting thing we know about רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is
he was very conservative. Like, you know, the גמרא Gemara says right
exactly, לעולם לא אמר דבר שלא שמע מפי רבו. le'olam lo amar
davar shelo shama mipi rabo. So, meaning that so, you know, any
teaching he always like interpreted it, like, you know, in its narrow
in a very narrow scope. He didn't feel he had the latitude
to to, you know, abstract and expand, and certainly not to sort
of innovate things on his own. So that might explain a little
bit about this. Everybody agrees the teaching was בשבת. beshabbos. Everybody agrees
the teaching was by a minor, and he's adopting the more conservative
read of that. But yes, it's surprising, things that we take for
granted he rejects. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: מתניתין מני
רבי יהודה היא. matnitin mani Rabbi Yehuda hi. Our משנה mishna that
phrased has this as the debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda version of their
debate. Okay? דתניא, detanya, we showed in a ברייתא. braita. רבי מאיר
אומר רבי אליעזר אומר. Rabbi Meir omer Rabbi Eliezer omer. So here's
רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir version of the debate. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says בכל דבריו קיימין מפני שיכול לכתוב אבל לא בשבת. bechol devarav
kayamin mipnei sheyachol lichtov aval lo beshabbos. So
it's still רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer limiting it, but the mirror image.
He limits it on חול chol it works because then it's like
taking the place of a written of a of a normal קניין
kinyan or a written קניין, kinyan, so therefore it's a time period
when קניין kinyan work, but it doesn't work on שבת. Shabbos. שבת
Shabbos is completely excluded from קניינים. kinyanim. So it's his mirror image,
but still limiting the application. רבי יהושע אומר בכל אמרו קל וחומר
בשבת. Rabbi Yehoshua omer bechol amru kal vachomer beshabbos.
Yes, I agree it started that they said this during the weekdays,
but if it'll work on a weekday, certainly they allowed it on
שבת Shabbos when there was no other option. So again, רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua is saying it applies all the time, רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer only part of the time, but the mirror image, only during
the weekdays, not on שבת. Shabbos. כיוצא בו, keyotzei bo, and he
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir also has the flip version or the mirror
image version of the case of זוכין. zochin. זוכין לגדול ואין זוכין
לקטן דברי רבי אליעזר. zochin legadol ve'ein zochin lekatan divrei Rabbi Eliezer.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it only works for the adult because
then you're could be seen as like his שליח, shaliach, but not
for the minor. How can you do for the minor if the
minor can't do it himself? So limiting the application, but in this
case limiting it to the adult. רבי יהושע אומר בגדול אמרו קל
וחומר לקטן. Rabbi Yehoshua omer begadol amru kal vachomer lekatan. No, they
said it by adult, certainly by a קטן katan who has no
other option, certainly they allowed. Okay, and again רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
applies it in both cases.
That's רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir version of the of the debate. רבי
יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says our version
of the debate. רבי אליעזר אומר בשבת ועל פי קיימן מפני שאין
יכול לכתוב אבל לא בכל. Rabbi Eliezer omer beshabbos ve'al pi kayaman
mipnei she'ein yachol lichtov aval lo bechol. It works only on שבת,
Shabbos, no other option, it doesn't work on the weekdays. רבי יהושע
אומר בשבת אמרו קל וחומר בכל. Rabbi Yehoshua omer beshabbos amru kal
vachomer bechol. Let it work on שבת, Shabbos, certainly they're going to
let it work during the weekdays. כיוצא בו זוכין לקטן ואין זוכין
לגדול דברי רבי אליעזר. keyotzei bo zochin lekatan ve'ein zochin legadol divrei
Rabbi Eliezer. Similarly, זוכין לקטן zochin lekatan and not זוכין לגדול, zochin
legadol, this is רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda version, the version of our
משנה. mishna. זכין *zakhen* works for a minor where there's no other
options but not for an adult; that's what רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*
says. רבי יהושע אומר לקטן אמר קל וחומר לגדול *Rabbi Yehoshua omer
l'katon amar kal v'chomer l'gadol*. They said for a minor, certainly for
an adult. And now the חלקת מחוקק'ס *Chelkas Mechokek's* very upset. Okay,
okay, moving on. Anyway, very fascinating to have these two versions of
this debate. Okay, now we get to a different point, which is
not, you know, moving beyond, no longer דברי שכיב מרע *divrei shchiv
mera*, I mean that had certainly been very dominant. And now we
sort of shift to—I don't know if we're totally done with this,
but we are certainly mostly done with it. I would have to
remind myself if we're totally done with it, but we're mostly done
with it, okay? And now we shift to a question of ירושה
*yerusha*, not the סדר ירושה *seder yerusha* בן בת *ben bat* etc.,
not שכיב מרע *shchiv mera* which is the rabbinic will and reordering
it... thank you, now be highly caffeinated, thank you... not the rabbinic
case but
the question of who died when and what happened in fact in
terms of how the ירושה *yerusha* took place. So let's take a
look. נפלו הבית עליו ועל אביו או עליו ועל מורישיו *naflu habayit
alav v'al aviv o alav v'al morishav*. So a house collapsed on
him—we'll use the רשב"ם'ס *Rashbam's* names—on ראובן Reuven *Reuven* and his father
יעקב Yaakov, *Yaakov*. Or on ראובן Reuven, *Reuven* and anybody else who
would be like a person who would bequeath him property, like his
mother, his brother, his uncle; but we're just going to deal with
the father, okay? The point is it doesn't have to be father;
father could be exchanged with anybody else who would be in a
position to bequeath him property. Is there an English word for מורישיו
*morishav*? A יורש *yoresh* is an heir. What's a מוריש morish, *morish*?
Is there a word for the other side of that equation?
I don't know. Okay, anyway. Does it have an English word for
מוריש *morish*?
You know, you'd say המנחיל *hamanchil*, one who...
right, thank you very much. Always interesting, you know, what the languages
have words for certain things. Like, you know, which languages have words
for the, what's it called, the מחותנים *mechutanim*? So, you know, I
think like Spanish has a word for that, you know, the parents
of your, you know, of your son-in-law or of your daughter-in-law or
whatever, you know, but English doesn't have a word for that. Like
it says something about, you know, the... what? המוריש *hamorish*? No, your
kids' in-laws.
Oh, so which shows a relationship between the parents of... anyway, whatever.
Okay, so anyway, the house fell on ראובן Reuven *Reuven* and on
יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov*. Now, והיתה עליו כתובת אשה ובעל חוב chov *v'hayta
alav ktuvat isha u'baal chov*. Now ראובן Reuven, *Reuven* was in debt,
okay? To creditors, to his ex-wife, okay? Now so here's the case
and presumably he had no money, okay? So here's your house,
here's your house, here's יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov*. We'll make יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov*,
since he's the dad we'll make him bigger, okay? Presumably they're both
adults. Here's ראובן Reuven's *Reuven*, okay?
What? You're going to draw a collapsed house?
Well, yes, he has an IOU, okay? And here's the creditor. Okay,
so anyway, so he owes him money, all right? And he has
no money. So what does the creditor want to happen? The creditor
wants—יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov* has money—so the creditor would like יעקב Yaakov *Yaakov*
to die first, then pass on his property to ראובן Reuven *Reuven*,
then ראובן *Reuven* would die, then the creditor would get a lien
on the property because now ראובן *Reuven* owns some property, then ראובן
*Reuven* would die, then let's say he would pass on his property
to his kids, okay? חנוך Hanoch *Chanoch*, excellent, you know your תנ"ך
*Tanakh*, okay? And then they could say, "Great, I got a lien
and now I'm going to collect my debt from חנוך Hanoch *Chanoch*."
That's what the creditor wants to happen. חנוך Hanoch, *Chanoch* does not
want that to happen. What חנוך Hanoch, *Chanoch* would rather have happen
is ראובן
*Reuven* died
first, then—so he—so then... well there's no property to pass on to
יעקב *Yaakov*, but whatever, any property he had would have gone anyway...
ראובן *Reuven* died first, then יעקב *Yaakov* died, and then חנוך Hanoch
*Chanoch* got it from יעקב *Yaakov*. Okay, and in that case he
got—there was no property that had any liens on it, right? You
got it? So either way חנוך Hanoch *Chanoch* is getting the property,
but he'd rather get it from his grandfather and not through his
father because if he gets it through his father, I guess his
father has no property, if he gets it through his father, right,
then here's the property and the question is which path did the
property take? So if the property went straight through יעקב *Yaakov*, the
creditor didn't get his hands on it. But if it went through
ראובן *Reuven*, then the creditor got a lien on it. So חנוך
Hanoch, *Chanoch* wants ראובן *Reuven* to die first and the creditor wants
יעקב *Yaakov* to die first. Yes?
Yes,
if there was no son, there was no חנוך Hanoch *Chanoch* and
ראובן *Reuven* died, would the property go to his father? Let's say
father was—didn't die. It would go to יעקב *Yaakov*, right?
Exactly, it would go.
Yeah, but if יעקב *Yaakov* was dead, then it would go to
whoever inherits from יעקב *Yaakov*. Okay, ראובן *Reuven*.
But what I'm asking is wouldn't the creditor have a lien on
the father—the property
that...
Yeah, but the son has no property.
The son doesn't have any property.
The only property here is יעקב's property. Okay.
Can I say these two things as different people? In other words,
to whatever it is, to this guy that's owed money, say oh
yeah, you know, whichever one. Right. But let's say for whatever other
reason, maybe advantageous to say the opposite. Right? Say the opposite to
someone else?
Oh, you mean if חנוך Hanoch had a claim, there were multiple
claims and it was in חנוך's Hanoch interest to say one thing
to one person and one to the other. Yeah, I mean, I
suppose you can, especially if you're operating from a המוציא מחבירו עליו
הראיה Hamotzi Mechaveiro Alav Hara'ayah perspective. You could say maybe it was
this way, prove to me the other way. If you have to
be the one that is doing the מוציא, motzi, and you're doing
it on the power of a טענת ברי, ta'anas bari, then it's
an interesting question. Yeah. Alright, let's take a look.
Yeah, the point is if the house doesn't fall down and everybody's
alive, there's no lien on, you don't go to the father. Correct.
Correct. Correct. Just to יעקב, there's a lien there.
Correct. Yeah. לא יומתו אבות על בנים ובנים לא יומתו על אבות.
Lo yamusu avos al banim ubanim lo yamusu al avos.
Okay, there you go. Okay. יורשי האב אומרים הבן מת ראשון. Yorshei
ha'av omrim haben mes rishon. So the heirs, those who inherit from
the father, we're going to simplify it. I mean, this would work
if there are other heirs as well, but we're going to simplify
it that the only person left standing here is חנוך, Hanoch okay?
יעקב has no other, if he had other kids it would also
work for them too. Fine, you know, but let's just simplify it,
okay? So יורשי האב Yorshei ha'av says הבן מת ראשון. haben mes
rishon. Okay, יעקב died, ראובן died first, and therefore the creditor didn't
get his hands on the property.
ואחר כך מת האב. Ve'achach mes ha'av. ובעלי חוב אומרים האב מת
ראשון, Uba'alei chov omrim ha'av mes rishon, and it passed down to
ראובן, and we got liens on it. ואחר כך מת הבן, Ve'achach
mes haben, and then the son died, and now we still have
liens on the property. בית שמאי אומרים יחלוקו, Beis Shammai omrim yachloku,
split the property. ובית הלל אומרים נכסים בחזקתן. Uveis Hillel omrim nechasim
bechezkasan. No, they remain in their חזקה, chazakah, which means in the
possession of the family, not in the possession of the creditors. Now,
interestingly, this גמרא Gemara is going to focus on a side point,
not on the basic debate of בית הלל בית שמאי. Beis Hillel
Beis Shammai. That basic debate is spelled out in another, in a
different גמרא, Gemara, and the basic point is like this. בית הלל
Beis Hillel makes of course totally the most sense, because whichever path
the property took, it's owned by חנוך, Hanoch, right? The only question
is, does the creditor have a lien on it? So המוציא מחבירו
עליו הראיה. Hamotzi Mechaveiro Alav Hara'ayah. I definitely own the property, you
have a ספק safek lien on it, you go prove to me
you've got a lien if you want to take it away from
me. Okay, so that's בית הלל's Beis Hillel position. הנכסים בחזקתן. Hanechasim
bechezkasam. I'm מוחזק. muchzak. The property, whichever path it took, I own
it. There's a question if you have a lien, המוציא מחבירו עליו
הראיה. Hamotzi Mechaveiro Alav Hara'ayah. בית שמאי Beis Shammai says, the way
the גמרא, Gemara, a different גמרא Gemara explains בית שמאי, Beis Shammai,
it's that שטר העומד לגבות כגבוי דמי. shtar ha'omed ligvos kigavu dami.
That it's not, it's if you have a שטר shtar and you
have a lien on property, it's like you have already collected the
property. So therefore, בית שמאי Beis Shammai would say, it's not true
that either way חנוך Hanoch owns the property. If the property took
this path, חנוך Chanoch owns it. If the property took this path,
when it went into ראובן's hands and I had a שטר, shtar,
then and I was, it was time to pay up, it was
like I had already taken possession. So, so right, meaning so even
if let's say חנוך, Chanoch it's somehow in חנוך's hands, I'm really
in possession. So it's not like either way חנוך is in possession
and there's a question if I have liens. If it took this
path, חנוך is in possession, and if it took this path, I
was, not just had liens, I was in possession. So therefore, יחלוקו.
yachloku. So that's בית שמאי's Beis Shammai position. Okay. If you say
it's like it's you're already in possession of it, then that makes
sense.
But I mean either way... Yeah. As if, as if שטר העומד
לגבות כגבוי דמי shtar ha'omed ligvos kigavu dami is the, undermines or
trumps המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi Mechaveiro Alav Hara'ayah.
Well, it doesn't trump, it redefines who's the מוציא. motzi. If it's
כגבוי, kigavu, then the חנוך is being, trying to be מוציא motzi
it from me. From this perspective, I'm trying to be מוציא motzi
it from חנוך, and from this perspective, חנוך is trying to be
מוציא motzi it from me. Right? עטשי. Atzish. Yeah. Okay.
Yeah. That's beautiful.
But even according to בית הלל, Beis Hillel, I mean, we still
do say
מצוה לפרוע חוב אביהם, mitzvah lifroa chov avihem, right? So he should
pay back.
And the גמרא Gemara is going to discuss that.
Let's see the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, תנן התם, tenan hasham, we talk over there.
המלווה את חבירו בשטר גובה מנכסים משועבדים. Hamalveh es chaveiro bishtar goveh
minechasim meshubadim. Okay, if you have a loan with a שטר, shtar,
שטר shtar is considered to come with it to create liens on
the property. So therefore you can collect from the, like liened property,
from the real estate even if it's now been sold to a
third party. על ידי עדים, Al yedei edim, it was only with
witnesses without a שטר, shtar, גובה מנכסים בני חורין. goveh minechasim benei
chorin. You can only collect from free property, unencumbered property, meaning property
that... well, no, it's קרקע, karka, but it's in the hands of
the original debtor. You cannot collect from property once it is from
a לוקח, lokei'ach, from a third party. Okay, now בעי שמואל... bayei
Shmuel...
meaning it can be either קרקע karka or movables?
Yeah, sure.
The basic way to think about this is that the existence of
the שטר shtar. *shtar* or the creating of the loan with the
presence of the שטר shtar *shtar* creates liens, right? So liens are
created on existing property, okay? So I own a certain number of
plots of land, okay, here I am here, right, and I own
these various plots of land, okay, and then I go ahead and
I borrow money and I give you a שטר shtar *shtar*,
and at that moment I borrowed money on this day, January 1,
okay, that did, that created on that day that I borrowed the
money and it was with a שטר shtar, *shtar*, that created these
various liens on my property. Okay, right, got it? Okay. So now
שמואל *Shmuel* has the following question. Let's say on January 15 or
whatever, January 15, I go ahead and I buy another piece of
property.
Okay,
do you have liens on that piece of property? No, so at
the moment of the loan which this created the liens, then I
didn't have that piece of property, so presumably you wouldn't have those
liens. Let's say however on this day when I'm borrowing I'm saying
I'm hereby like giving you liens on everything I own and that
eventually I will own. Does that phrase sound familiar? דאקני d'aknei.
דעתיד אנא למקני *D'iknei d'asid ana l'miknei*.
Yeah, that's in the כתובה *ketubah*. What does the כתובה *ketubah* say?
It says דקנאי ודעתיד אנא למקני *D'kanai u'd'asid ana l'miknei*, אפילו גלימא
דעל
כתפיה *Afilu glima d'al kispeh*, right, למקני *l'miknei*. דחסין ודאיתא להון אחריות
achrayut ודלא איתא
להון אחריות *D'chassin v'deiso l'hon achrayus v'delo
iso l'hon achrayus*,
okay,
you explicitly say I'm hereby giving you loans on future property. Does
that work? What created those liens, okay? When I was here I
didn't have the property to give you the liens on the property.
What created those liens? Well, that is the question. So let's take
a look. בעי שמואל *Ba'ei Shmuel*, so שמואל *Shmuel* asked, דאקני דעתיד
אנא למקני דאקני *D'iknei d'asid ana l'miknei d'iknei*, if I say I
will have liens on property I will purchase, וקנה *v'kanah*, and we
do a קנין *kinyan*, like we do a קנין סודר *kinyan sudar*
to make it binding, okay, מהו *mahu*,
what's the הלכה halakha *halacha*? אליבא דרבי מאיר *Aliba d'Rabbi Meir*, as
Michael figured it out again, דאמר אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם
makneh davar shelo ba l'olam. *d'amar adam makneh davar she'lo ba l'olam*,
if you can sell stuff that you don't yet own, okay, that's
pretty obvious you should be able to create liens on property you
don't yet own.
If you say אפילו פירות
דקל *Afilu peirot dekel*, oy, Michael you're too smart. Okay, but anyway,
so תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* deals with the fact about maybe it's only
עבידי דאתו *avidi d'asu*, this isn't עבידי דאתו *avidi d'asu*. On the
other hand this already exists, fruit doesn't exist yet, this isn't a
real ownership, this is just a lien. Fine, within the world of
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. *Rabbi Meir* we could make it work, at
least as a general some power to create a קנין *kinyan* on
something you don't yet own. כי תיבעי לך *Ki tiba'ei lach*, when
do I want to know? אליבא דרבנן *Aliba d'Rabbanan* דאמרי אין אדם
מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם *d'amri ein adam makneh davar she'lo ba
l'olam*, you can't do something you don't yet own, so can you
do this? So the question is, well, the answer should be no.
Like if you can't be מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם *makneh davar
she'lo ba l'olam*, why should you be able to do this? So
if you look at the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*, he has two interesting
reasons why this should be possible. So the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* says,
אלא ela,
*ela*, three lines down in the medium-sized lines, or four lines down,
beginning of the fourth line in the medium-sized lines, אלא כי תיבעי
לך אליבא דרבנן מאי *ela ki tiba'ei lach aliba d'Rabbanan mai*, מי
שאני שיעבוד מקנין *mi shani shibud mi'kinyan*, okay, number one, I'm not
really selling you, transferring property I'll get later, I'm just giving you
a שיעבוד *shibud* on it, so maybe that's something that's more an
abstraction and it's not real ownership and maybe somehow that's more possible.
Okay, וטעמא כדפרישית *v'tama k'deperishis*, אי נמי *ei nami*, so
number one is a שיעבוד *shibud* is different than ownership and that
I could pre-give you before I have the property. אי נמי *Ei
nami*, אמור רבנן לשיעבוד יוסר מקנין *amur Rabbanan l'shibud yoseir mi'kinyan*, they
especially created the opportunity to do this, even though logically you shouldn't
be able to, דלא תינעול דלת בפני לווין *d'lo tinal delet bifnei
lovin*. Why? In order to encourage people to lend money. Okay, so
therefore, maybe the Rabbis just said it works. All right, so yes,
logically you shouldn't be able to, but the Rabbis said it works,
and that allows people gives people greater freedom to feel that they
can lend money
because they have some security that they can get paid back in
the future.
Right, not security because you don't know he'll buy more stuff, but
it increases the likelihood. Right,
exactly. Okay, so now that's שמואל *Shmuel's* question. So let's take a
look.
So the instrument is the authority of the Rabbis, right.
I mean, well, yes, it's backed through a קנין *kinyan* that they
do and they explicate and they say it, you know, it's not
like magic out of thin air, but ultimately right, right, the Rabbis
gave that power to that מעשה קנין *maaseh kinyan*, right. Okay, so
אמר רב יוסף תא שמע Ta shema, *Amar Rav Yosef ta shema*,
come and hear. וחכמים אומרים *V'chachamim omrim* זה היה פיקח שמכר לו
את הקרקע *zeh haya pikeach shemachar lo es hakarka* מן שיכול למשכנו
עליו *min sheyachol l'mashkeno alav*. So here's what happened: Michael comes to
me and shows an IOU that I owe him ten thousand dollars
and I borrowed this money on January 1st. And I say, Michael,
that שטר shtar *shtar* is clearly a forgery, and I'm going to
prove it to you because I've got this document that on February
1st I bought from you a piece of land for ten thousand
dollars. Now, Michael, if I really owed you that ten thousand dollars,
why the heck did you sell me that land for ten thousand
dollars? You should have just taken my money in payment. Okay? That's
a pretty reasonable position. So Admon says that proves your שטר shtar
*shtar* is a forgery, okay, because why else would you have accepted
money for land when you could have just taken the money for
payment of a debt? וחכמים אומרים *V'chachamim omrim* זה היה פיקח *zeh
haya pikeach*.
No, Michael is very smart. Why was Michael very smart? Right. זה
היה פיקח *zeh haya pikeach*... I lost my place... זה היה פיקח
שמכר לו את הקרקע *zeh haya pikeach shemachar lo es hakarka* מפני
שיכול למשכנו עליו *mipnei sheyachol l'mashkeno alav*. Michael said like this: Look,
if I say to Dove, where's my ten... where's my money? You
owe me the money. He'll say what money, where? I don't have
any money, I'm broke. Okay? Go prove to me I have the
ten. Michael heard I just got... came into some money, I have
ten thousand dollars. He's going to come after me for it, I'm
going to tell him I'm broke. How's he going to get it
out of me? How's he going to prove I have it? So
he... what he really does, he's very smart. He sells me a
plot of land for ten thousand dollars. He pockets the cash. Then
he's going to come tomorrow, like he just did, with the שטר
shtar חוב chov *shtar chov*, and I can't tell him I don't
have any money because I have a plot of land. I can't
hide a plot of land. So Michael was very smart, okay? He
got the cash out of my hand which otherwise I would have
hidden away, and now he's got a piece of property that he
can collect in his debt. All right, so that's what the חכמים
Chakhamim *chachamim* say. זה היה פיקח שמכר לו את הקרקע *zeh haya
pikeach shemachar lo es hakarka* מפני שיכול למשכנו *mipnei sheyachol l'mashkeno*. The
land you can take as... למשכנו *mashkeno* literally means as collateral, but
it means the land is present and he can collect his debt
from the land without me being able to hide it.
עליו *alav*. That land will now serve as a lien to the
debt, the previous debt. Right, even though he didn't... the debtor didn't
own that land at...
So Dove is figuring out why the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is quoting
this. How can Michael collect his debt from that piece of land?
I only came into possession of that piece of land after the
debt. Right. So there you see it can work. There are ways
in which he can get a lien on something that I come
into possession with later. אמר ליה רבא *Amar lei Rava*, so Rava
said back: מיניה *minei*? From him? From the debtor himself? That was
never debated. Michael can collect anything that I've got in my possession,
whenever I got it in my possession.
מיניה *minei*? מיניה אפילו מגלימא דעל כתפיה *minei afilu miglima d'al katfei*.
See, we're getting the לשון *lashon* of the כתובה *Kesuvah*. He can
even rip the shirt off of my back. Okay? It doesn't matter
from property that I own. It doesn't matter קרקע karka. *karka*, doesn't
matter מטלטלין metaltelin, *metaltelin*, what? Yeah, doesn't matter when I came into
possession of it. He... I owe him the money, he can always
collect from money that I have in my possession. The issue of
liens is when somebody else now owns it. Okay, so if I
got this piece of land from Michael, of course he can take
it back from me. The question is, I got the land and
sold it to someone else. Then the question is does he have
liens on it?
Okay. דאיקני de'ikne *d'ikni*. What we want to know is דאיקני de'ikne,
קנה ומכר *d'ikni kana umachar*. I say land that I will future
take possession of, we did a קנין *kinyan* and then I got
possession... oh, actually דאיקני Da'iknei, *d'ikni*. I've been reading קנה *kana* here,
I might have misread it. I read קנה *kana* that you did
a קנין *kinyan* like a קנין סודר *kinyan sudar* to make it
binding. But it might mean דאיקני Da'iknei, *d'ikni* and then you were
קנה *kana*, then you actually קונה *koneh* the land. Yeah, I think
I misread that. So anyway, okay. דאיקני *d'ikni*, I say to Michael,
land that I will come in possession of, קנה *kana*, I do
take possession of new land, ומכר *umachar*, and then I sold it,
okay? And now the question is, while I was in possession, of
course he could take it from me, but now it's been sold.
Did he get liens on it when it went through my hands
and when I got it after the loan? Or דאיקני *d'ikni*, I
say that I will take possession of, קנה *kana*, and then I
actually do buy new land, והוריש *vehoreish*, or not me, it's somebody
else anyway, they die and then they bequeath it. Does the creditor
get liens that now he can take it even in the hands
of a third party, from the יורש *yoresh*? From the יורש *yoresh*,
what's the הלכה *halacha*?
So אמר רב
חנא *Amar Rav Chana*, תא שמע *ta shema*, come and hear.
נפל הבית עליו ועל אביו עליו ועל מורישיו והיתה עליו כתובת אשה
ובעל חוב
*Nafal habayis alav v'al aviv alav v'al morishav vehaysa alav kesubas isha
uva'al chov*. יורשי אב אומרים הבן מת ראשון ואחר כך מת האב
*yorshei av omrim haben mes rishon v'achar kach mes ha'av* ובעל חוב
אומרים האב מת ראשון ואחר כך מת הבן *uba'al chov omrim ha'av
mes rishon v'achar kach mes haben*. Our case. So remember,
what does the creditor want? He wants Yaakov to die first, so
that Reuven gets the property, so he gets a lien on the
property, and then can collect it from Chanoch, right, after Reuven dies.
Everybody get that? Right? How did the creditor get a lien on
it just from it went from Yaakov to Reuven? That was property
that Reuven came into possession of after the loan. Right? So even
if Yaakov died first and the property passed to Reuven... Where did
those liens come from? The loan already exists, and now he's going
to use those liens to collect it from חנוך. So that's a
pretty good proof that you can get liens on property that was
taken possession of after the loan. Right? So ואי סלקא דעתך דאיקני
קנה ומכר, ve'i salka da'atach de'ikne kana umachar, if you say דאיקני
then you take possession and sell, דאיקני קנה והוריש, de'ikne kana vehorish,
take possession and be מוריש, לא משתעבד, lo mishta'abed, that the property
does not get liens attached to it. נהי נמי דמית ברישא, nehi
nami de'mit be'reisha, let יעקב have died first. דאיקני הוא. de'ikne hu.
It's at best the case of דאיקני, but you're saying that doesn't
create liens, new liens. So how are the creditors going to get
it? Pretty darn good proof. So אמר להו רב נחמן זעירא חברין
תרגמה, amar lehu Rav Nachman Zeira chaveirein targama, so Rav Nachman said
Zeira our friend, our colleague,
translated this משנה, mishna, said it was a case of מצוה על
היתומים לפרוע חובות אביהן. mitzvah al hayesomim lifroa chovot avihen. That's what
Michael was saying. Maybe it could be that there are no real
liens. But חנוך here has a מצוה, mitzvah, now the question is
is it a moral or a legal obligation to pay off his
father's debt. Now the תוספות Tosafot clarifies that there are, and it's
very implicit in this גמרא, Gemara two degrees of this מצוה לפרוע
חובות אביהן. mitzvah lifroa chovot avihen. One is the father left them
no property, but nevertheless, or he only left them מטלטלין, and the
creditors only have liens on the קרקע. Okay, so the creditors are
out all their money.
But that is not doing right by the creditors and to some
degree it's not even doing right by the father; their father is
now this deadbeat and so on. So he's not only dead, he's
a deadbeat. So they should go ahead and do the right thing
and pay off their creditors. Like some people even after they declare
bankruptcy, they actually, there are stories of like they really try to
pay off all their
creditors if over the course of their lives or whatever. I borrowed
the money, it's a moral obligation. Okay, so that's one thing. That's
like from their own pocket. That's a moral obligation. בית דין Beit
Din would never enforce it. But if it is coming, if they
inherited from their father, okay, then the מצוה mitzvah to pay back
the creditors with the father's money, with the father's estate, that's actually
a type of a legal obligation and בית דין Beit Din would
actually enforce it. Now the funny thing is what's not clear
is why do you need that
מצוה? mitzvah? Like the creditor already has liens on the estate, so
it's not exactly clear why you would need that מצוה mitzvah if
the liens already exist. But what it does is it means that
the sort of obligation, it's not just that he has a right
to property, there's also a personal
obligation that the heirs have. But it's not so clear what the
major נפקא מינה nafka mina is once there actually exist liens. Okay,
but this is, the גמרא Gemara first is assuming that there's a
gap between those. It says, look, it's true that if it passes
through ראובן, he doesn't get liens, because we're assuming you can't get
liens after the debt. But since it still was ראובן's property, they
should be paying up the creditor. So the creditors say they want
it to happen this way and say, since it happened this way
and you inherited property from your father, even though I don't have
any liens on those property, since you inherited from your father, you
have a moral and maybe even a legally binding obligation to pay
off your father's debts with the property. So even though there's no
liens, it's your personal obligation to pay off the debt with the
property you got. And that's why I wanted to go this way.
Yes.
I like calling it a legal rather than a moral obligation, in
other words another legal vehicle to enable the creditor to, instead of
the creditor taking, the possessor's obligated to give.
Correct. So the difference is that's what there are two types of
מצוה mitzvah though, תוספות says. If it's you did not get property
from your father, your father left you debts but didn't leave you
any property, then it's just a moral obligation, it's not enforceable. If
you got property from your father, okay, and then now it's paying
off your father's debts with that property even though there are no
liens, that's an actual enforceable obligation. But it's on you the person,
it's not on the property. I don't have liens on the property,
but since you got your father's property, you're now obligated to pay
off the debt.
Yes. The way you framed it, formulated it is very interesting to
me. I don't know if you did it intentionally. Probably not. Yeah.
Something in the realm of a moral obligation by definition is not
enforceable through a legal mechanism.
Well, if it's only a moral obligation. Obviously there
are.
A moral obligation has a certain gravitas but unenforceable through a legal
instrument. Right. That's very interesting. Yeah.
I mean, but that's, but it's less because you're calling it a
moral obligation, because you're saying it's only moral and not legal. So
therefore, because a lot of things are like both.
Would it make a difference depending on whether it's moral or legal
if the, we didn't give him a name, but that creditor then
sells the... to somebody else. If you're saying it's moral because of
a personal obligation, then
you don't have a personal... Yeah, but I'm not sure. No, no,
I'm saying the obligation creates the nature of the obligation is personal.
I don't mean because of the personal relationship. The obligation is my
sort of to clear
the name of my father. But the nature of the obligation is
this leans toward a relationship to property. This is an obligation of
the person, not personal relationship. It's an obligation on the person.
Yes. To have something encumbered has to be an act that the
owner of it encumbers it, he allows it to have a lien?
Essentially, that's how it's understood. Okay.
And if he doesn't make that conscious statement?
Or implicit by borrowing money and writing a שטר. Right. Yes. Correct.
That's what seems to be the understanding. Yes. Okay. So that's so
he says the reason the creditor wants it to go this way
is to create this מצוה mitzvah obligation on the kid because now
the kid has father's property even though it has no liens. So
now the גמרא Gemara is going to push back and say there
is no enforceable מצוה mitzvah obligation without liens. Okay, which then raises
the question who needs the מצוה mitzvah obligation? But this is what
the גמרא's Gemara response is going to be. Okay. מתקיף לה רב
אשי, matkif lah Rav Ashi, Rav Ashi challenges. מלוה על פה הוא,
milveh al peh hu, once you say that there are no liens,
you're effectively making it like an oral loan, right? Meaning an oral
loan is a loan that doesn't have liens attached to it. Okay.
So now the חוב that חנוך owes the creditor is like he
owed him just with an oral loan because there meaning it's a
חוב with no liens. All right. So מלוה על פה הוא ורב
ושמואל דאמרי תרווייהו מלוה על פה אינו גובה לא מן היורשים ולא
מן הלקוחות. milveh al peh hu v'Rav uShmuel d'amri tarveihu milveh al
peh eino goveh lo min hayorshim v'lo min halakochot. If there's just
an oral loan and there are no liens, then the creditors cannot
collect from the heirs. And this presumably means now you could just
say it means that there are no liens. But the גמרא Gemara
interprets it to mean and there's not even this מצוה לפרוע חוב
אביהן. mitzvah lifro'a chov avihen. Okay. Which so really the response is
that this מצוה mitzvah to pay the father's debt in this enforceable
way is limited to a case where there are liens. Which then
raises the question who needs the מצוה mitzvah if there are liens?
Okay, so I don't know, that's not so clear, but that's the
response. So the first answer was a pretty good one. Okay, there
are no liens, but since it went through the father, it creates
this מצוה mitzvah to pay it up. And the answer is if
you're telling me there are no liens, there's no there might be
the moral idea to pay off the father's debt. That's true even
for money from their own pockets. But there's no enforceable obligation for
them to pay. So we're back to square one. If there are
no liens, what good did it do that יעקב died first? And
let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is. אלא, says the גמרא
Gemara on the עמוד ב. amud bet. הא מני רבי מאיר היא
דאמר אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם. ha mani Rabbi Meir hi
d'amar adam makneh davar shelo ba l'olam. So now any proof pretty
much that you're going to bring from any source that shows that
you can create liens on property that you got after the loan,
we have this answer in our back pocket. Oh, that's רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir, Okay, since we said that there's obviously a possibility according
to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir any time we see that, we can
always just claim it's a רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. position. So the
claim is here you're right. This משנה Mishna makes it clear that
if the יעקב died first and then ראובן got it, that the
creditor has liens. We will say that that was a case where
number one, the שטר explicitly said
דאקני. Okay, or whatever דאקני אנא למקני, d'akni ana lemaknei, same point,
דאקני אנא למקני. d'akni ana lemaknei. The שטר said it. Number one.
And number two, it's going according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir So
that's how our משנה Mishna works that the creditor gets liens afterwards.
Okay. רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir principle works even if it's a מלוה
על
פה?
milveh
al peh?
No, with a מלוה על פה milveh al peh you don't have
liens. Because he asked you created liens, there was a שטר, you
explicitly said and you have to be explicit. A normal שטר wouldn't
be liens in the future. But you explicitly said and I am
creating liens in the future and that works plus רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir. who says מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם. Okay. So any case
where we have a case where it seems like you have liens
on property that the guy got later, we can always claim that
it was the combination of saying that explicitly, but not because that
itself works according to everyone because but because we're working within the
position of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir? Okay.
Even on property that you own now you still have to say
in the document this is a lien on this?
No, that's a debate in the גמרא Gemara and we פוסקין אחריות
טעות סופר poskin achrayut ta'ut sofer that the very existence of a
שטר creates liens even if liens are not explicit. But if you
want to create liens in the future you have to be explicit.
And now the question is does that work according to everybody or
just according to רבי מאיר?
Rabbi Meir I'm reading this that because on רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir.
authority you can write this in the שטר and that No, Rabbi
Meir is explicating the principle based on common practice in his, right?
He's not describing. No.
No, because Rabbi Meir never even said this. We're just combining a
Rabbi Meir with this case, you know. All right. So now the
גמרא *Gemara* says like this. אמר רבי יעקב מנהר פקוד *Amar Rabbi
Yaakov min Nahar Pekod*, said Rabbi Yaakov from the river of Pekod,
משמיה דרבינא *mishmei de'Ravina*, תא שמע *ta shema*, שטרי חוב המוקדמים פסולים
והמאוחרים כשרים *Shtarei hov hamukdamim pesulim vehamukharim kesherim*. This is now here
we go. I borrowed money on this date that create liens. Let's
say I predated the document. Okay. You could predate a check, postdate
etc. Let's say I predated and even though I borrowed on January
15th, I wrote in the document January 1st, okay, of the same
year, whatever. I mean I guess of the previous year.
Wait, January 15th and January 30th? Fine.
Okay well then we'll make this January 15th.
I can only deal with one variable.
Got it. Okay fine.
I
wrote in the document January 1st. Okay now that's פסול *pasul*. You
know why it's פסול *pasul*? Yes, because I know you know why.
Okay, the reason it's פסול *pasul* is the following. Because let's say
what actually happened is back here when it actually was January 1st,
here it is, it actually is January 1st, and what I did
on that day was I sold this piece of property I had,
I sold it to this nice little innocent purchaser. And this guy
did the right thing, he did a what's it called, a title
check, a title search. He found out that there's I had no
liens on my property. He bought this property, he knew he was
safe from any creditors. Okay, and then 15 days later I borrow
money and I predate it to January 1st. So now I am
claiming that this guy has liens from way back here and he's
gonna use that against this guy who bought property that had no
liens against him. So that's פסול *pasul*, okay. שטרי חוב המוקדמים פסולים
*Shtarei hov hamukdamim pesulim*, number one. Number two is תוספות *Tosafot* actually
has a question, can you even use the שטר *shtar* to collect
money from the guy himself? Do we completely rip up the שטר
*shtar* or do we just say the liens in the שטר *shtar*
are פסולים *psulim*? That's an interesting question but let's pass for ignore
that.
You actually have it, it could be פסולים *psulim* but it means
not.
Yeah well he says language פסולים *psulim* sounds like you totally rip
it up but he raises the possibility it just means we won't
use it with its liens. But it makes obviously the פשט Peshat
*pshat* is we rip it up. Okay number one. Now how about
if I predated it? How about if in here I postdated it?
Thank you. I wrote January 30th. So
so I'm just hurting myself right? Because what I'm doing is that
I am I mean what he the creditor is hurting himself because
what what I am allowing you to do what I let's make
me the creditor what I'm allowing you to do is I'm allowing
you to sell off all as much property as you can in
the next 15 days and I won't have any liens on it.
Right. So therefore that's kosher. But now the גמרא *Gemara* has an
interesting question. Here's the גמרא *Gemara*'s question. What would happen though if
I
why would the creditor agree to that?
I don't know he's a nice guy I really have no idea.
That's that's not our business.
I have no idea I really don't know why he would agree
to that. But that's not always interest. Okay fine. Let's say though
so that we understand why it's kosher because what I'm really doing
is I'm just forfeiting my liens for 15 days. But the גמרא
*Gemara* says but you're doing more than forfeiting your liens for 15
days because let's say on January 25th I go ahead
the I not I
the the borrower goes ahead and buys himself another piece of property
on January 25th. Okay if I had said properly dated the שטר
*shtar* January 15th right then assuming that liens don't exist in the
future only in the present would the the creditor have liens on
it? No. But now because I dated it on January 30th I'm
giving him and it's gonna look like he borrowed the money on
the 30th I'm gonna give him liens on this piece of property.
So how it could work to the creditor's advantage?
For new property. Right. But the גמרא *Gemara*'s saying is but how
is it kosher unless there's a mechanism to actually give him liens
on future property? Right. So the fact that we allow this which
will have the effect of making him have liens on property I
buy in the interim indicates that there is ways to create liens
in the future.
At least according to Rabbi Meir.
Well that's always the back pocket answer. Okay so the גמרא *Gemara*
says like this: ואי סלקא דעתך דאקני קנה ומכר לא משתעבד Lo
mishta'abed, *ve-isalkah daitakh
de-ikni kana umakhar lo mishtabed* מאוחרים אמאי כשרים *mukharim amai kesherim* דאקני
הוא
*de-ikni d'hu* that will affect property you buy after you know in
the interim. So הא מני רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. היא *Ha mani
Rabbi Meir hi* דאמר *de-amar*. אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם.
Now we can get out of any question by just saying it's
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir, Okay, אמר רב משרשיא משמיה דרבא, Amar Rav
Mesharshya mishmei de-Rava, so let's try again. תא שמע, come and hear.
Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait. What are we trying to do? We're
trying to disprove?
We're trying to say you cannot prove that everybody agrees that you
can create future liens. Maybe all evidence of future liens is only
according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir And if we don't פוסקין pasken
רבי מאיר, Rabi Meir, then maybe you can't create future liens.
So
you're trying to find a case in which according to חכמים we're
trying to say it works.
Right, now exactly. Which is going to be a hard proof because
unless you have explicitly a non-רבי מאיר position, you know, how are
you going to be able to prove it? So let's keep on
see where the גמרא's going to
go. Okay, אמר תא שמע, Amar ta shema, come and hear. בשבח
קרקעות כיצד? Be-shevach karkaot keitzad? Now the הלכה is that
that
somebody cannot have liens, there are a series of things that you
can't have liens, a series of debts as it were, that the
Rabbis did not allow liens to operate for, that the person could
only collect from property in the person, you know, in the person
who owes the money, his own control but not in the hands
of third parties. Why are these? These are particularly things that there
is a non-fixed amount. And if there's a non-fixed amount, it is
not fair to the poor purchasers to have to know that there
are that there are going to be liens, but the amount of
the lien is not determined. So when the amount that's owed, you
know, the amount of the debt is indeterminate, there are no liens.
Okay, what's an example of this? An example of this is the
following: I go ahead and I sell to my friend there Yisrael,
I sell him some land. Now I insure it, which means that
if a creditor comes and takes that land, or the land is
discovered to be stolen, I will reimburse him for it. Okay, now,
problem is that it's all very nice. You know, it's sort of
like when you go ahead, I remember this, when you know when
you remember those things called floppy disks? And remember the time when
you used to have floppy disks or hard drives or whatever, and
they said like, "We insure this against data loss. If, you know,
if ever like whatever the data gets lost, we will give you
a new floppy disk." Like, "Thank you very much, I don't care
about the floppy disk!" So, okay. So anyway, so Yisrael there says
it's not enough to tell me that you're going to reimburse me
if this land gets taken away from me. If it's discovered to
be stolen or whatever, and I've invested a million dollars in improvements,
I want to be reimbursed for my improvements. Okay, so I say
fine, I'll insure you against that as well. Okay, that's שבח קרקעות.
shevach karkaot. But we but that's a non-determinant
amount. How much is he going to improve?
Okay, so like, "Okay, I'm going to improve it by a million
dollars."
But you don't say that. You say however much that שבח shevach
is. So Yisrael's right to collect, his insurance creates liens because he's
going now have to collect that from me. And let's say I
don't have the cash available, I've sold property. So he has liens
on my property to pay for his insurance. Okay, but the liens
are only for the value of the property itself. For the שבח
קרקעות, shevach karkaot, for the increased value, he can collect from me
directly, but he cannot collect from third parties. Okay, people sort of
get that scenario?
He can only collect for...
it's the אחריות for the value of the land he can collect
from third parties, that creates liens. The שבח shevach does not create
liens. Okay, because and he can collect only from me
directly. Okay, so, בשבח קרקעות כיצד, Be-shevach karkaot keitzad, how does this
work? הרי שמכר שדה לחבירו, Harei she-machar sadeh le-chavero,
I sold this land to my friend Yisrael there, והשביחה, ve-hishbichah, and
he improved it. ובא בעל חוב וטרפה. U-va ba'al chov ve-tarfah.
Now, comes along Michael, and Michael, it's not he doesn't say this
field was stolen, Michael says, "Very nice, Dov owed me a million
dollars before he sold you that plot of land. I am taking
that plot of land. Thank you very much." That plot of land
with all the improvements is taken away. And now Yisrael wants to
come and get reimbursed from me.
ובא בעל חוב, U-va ba'al chov, okay, וטרפה, ve-tarfah, כשהוא גובה גובה
את
הקרן מנכסים משועבדין,
ke-she-hu goveh goveh
et ha-keren mi-nechasim meshu'abadin,
so Yisrael can collect the actual principal, the value of the land,
from encumbered property, property that I've sold, ואת השבח מנכסים בני חורין,
ve-et ha-shevach mi-nechasim benei chorin,
but any improvements he can only collect from property that is free,
that's under my control directly, not in the hands of third parties.
Fine. What's interesting to us is not where Yisrael can collect from.
What's interesting to us is, if Michael is a creditor... it's one
thing if Michael said the property was stolen. If Michael's a creditor,
how did he collect the land, not just the land from Yisrael,
but also the improvement? Well, you can't take
the land without the improvement. Well, you can pay him back the
improvement. You can take the... pay him the
difference. But he didn't, he took it all! Okay. He can't do
that if it's in excess of a loan. How could... well, no,
it wasn't in excess of a loan, okay? But so it's not
in excess of a loan, there's an option to pay him back
the improvements and you didn't, you just took the whole land with
the improvements. How did you do that? You only had a lien
on the land. I had borrowed a million dollars from you before
I sold it, but it didn't have the improvements at that time.
The fact that he has a right to collect his loan from
the שבח Shevach proves that when he borrowed the money from me,
I could create future liens. That's right. And therefore you have liens
not only on the land but on its future improvements. דאיקני מה
דעתיד למיקני. Da'iknei mah de'asid lemiknei. Exactly. דאי סלקא דעתך דאיקני קנה
ומכר דאיקני קנה והוריש לא משתעבד. De'i salka da'atach da'iknei kana umachar
da'iknei kana vehoreish lo mishta'abed. So if you say that you cannot
create future liens, במאי גובה שבחא? B'mai goveih shivcha? How was Michael
able to pay up, collect payment of his debt from the improvements?
הא מני רבי מאיר היא דאמר אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם.
Ha mani Rabi Meir hi de'amar adam makneh davar she'lo ba l'olam.
Okay whatever. Any proof you give me I'll just say רבי מאיר,
but obviously the evidence is stacking up that there's a lot of
cases where it seems like you can create future liens. I'm going
to hold the questions because I want to get to the end
of the דף. Daf. אם תמצי לומר, Im timtzei lomar, fine, so
we're not going to prove it, but we sort of know, all
the indications are that you can do that. So אם תמצי לומר
דאיקני קנה ומכר דאיקני קנה והוריש לא משתעבד, Im timtzei lomar da'iknei
kana umachar da'iknei kana vehoreish lo mishta'abed, but if you were to
say that you could not do it, לא משתעבד, Lo mishta'abed, fine,
it doesn't work, so I'm not going to have the following question.
But אם תמצי לומר משתעבד, Im timtzei lomar mishta'abed, if you say
that you can create future liens, which is where all the evidence
is pointing, that you can create future liens, I have the following
question: לוה לוה וחזר וקנה מהו? Lava lava vachazar vekana mahu? Let's
say you create two future liens with two different people, okay? So
here's this case, okay? I go ahead and on January 1, here's
the creditor, on January 1, I say to this guy, you know,
דאיקני, future property, and then on January 15, I say to a
different person, we'll draw them in a different whatever, I also say
דאיקני, okay? And then on January 30, I actually bought some property,
okay? So לוה לוה וחזר וקנה, Lava lava vachazar vekana, okay? Who
has liens on that property? So you could say—but the liens only
came into existence on January 30. So if it was on pre-existing
property, property I already own, the principle is the first guy in
wins, he has a prior lien, so his rights precede his rights.
That's on existing property, right? So existing property, the person with the
earlier lien wins because your rights preceded his. But in this case,
the liens weren't materialized until January 30, and maybe both of them
jump in at the same time. Okay, does it work that way
or does it not work that way? So let's take a look.
אם תמצי לומר Im timtzei lomar again. Yeah. אם תמצי לומר דאיקני
קנה ומכר דאיקני קנה והוריש לא משתעבד, Im timtzei lomar da'iknei kana
umachar da'iknei kana vehoreish lo mishta'abed, if it doesn't create liens, לא
משתעבד, then fine, it doesn't create liens and we don't have any—our
inquiry ends. I mean, we're about to ask a hypothetical, and this
hypothetical is only relevant if you say that it does create liens.
If it doesn't create liens, fine, end of the discussion. So we
haven't proved it to anybody. Nothing has been proven, but now we're
just exploring. אם תמצי לומר משתעבד, Im timtzei lomar mishta'abed, but if
it does create liens, לוה לוה וחזר וקנה מהו? Lava lava vachazar
vekana mahu? קמא משתעבד? Kama mishta'abed? Does it go to the first
person? Because normally we say first person with liens wins, okay? או
דלמא בתרא משתעבד? O dilma basra mishta'abed? Or the last guy, or
more logically both equally. Well, it's—right, the פשט of the question is
only the last guy, so the רשב"ם says maybe since it didn't
take effect yet, then we say it's like I retracted from the
first guy and award to the second, and maybe it's only the
second. וחזר? Vachazar? Well, חזר Chazar just means after this. But okay.
אמר רב נחמן הדין מילתא איבעיא לן, Amar Rav Nachman hadein milta
ibaya lan, we asked this question, ושדרו מתם, Veshadru mitam, they sent
from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, ראשון קנה, Rishon kana, the first guy,
okay, like normal liens. רב הונא אמר יחלוקו, Rav Huna amar yachloku,
split it, which means they both get it equally. וכן תני רבה
בר אבוה יחלוקו, V'chein tani Rabba bar Avuha yachloku, split it. אמר
רבינא, Amar Ravina, מדורה קמא דרב אשי, Madura kama deRav Ashi, in
the first cycle of רב אשי, Rav Ashi, אמר לן ראשון קנה,
amar lan rishon kana, the first one gets it. מדורה בתרא דרב
אשי, Madura basra deRav Ashi, in his latter cycle of teaching, אמר
לן יחלוקו, amar lan yachloku, split it. Now that's by the way,
just have to stop and pause with that phrase because מדורה קמא,
Madura kama, מדורה בתרא, Madura basra, is a phrase that then gets
borrowed by later ראשונים Rishonim and אחרונים Acharonim or whatever, that you
know if you sort of come out with a first edition and
then a revised edition. Okay, so it's different than like קמא Kama
and—like the נודע ביהודה Noda Biyehuda classically has two volumes of ספרים,
Sfarim, נודע ביהודה קמא, Noda Biyehuda Kama, נודע ביהודה תנינא, Noda Biyehuda
Tinyana, but that's just volume one, volume two. מדורה קמא, Madura kama,
מדורה בתרא, Madura basra, is sort of like a second edition. Okay,
now there's a great רשב"ם that I just have to pause and
read inside if you— נמצא בתשובות רב האי ובפירוש רבנו חננאל *Nimtza
bi'Tshuvos Rav Hai u'be'Peirush Rabbeinu Chananel*, רב אשי חיה ששים שנה *Rav
Ashi chaya shishim shanah*. He lived 60 years. ובכל שנה מחזר לימודו
בשני חדשי הכלה ניסן ותשרי *u'vechol shanah mechazer limudo bi'shnei chodshei ha'kalah
Nissan ve'Tishrei* and on every time of the two months of Nissan
and Tishrei where they give public lectures before the חגים *Chagim*, he
would חזר *chazer* his learning. But he wouldn't חזר *chazer* all of
his learning during those months. He would devote that time to חזרה
*chazarah*. Okay. וכשהגיעו שלושים שנה סיים כל לימודו *u'chshe'higi'u shloshim shanah siyeim
kol limudo* because presumably since he's giving שיעורים *shiurim* on stuff he
already learned, he's not learning new material during that time, so when
he goes home in the night he does חזרה *chazarah*. Okay, anyway,
וכשהגיעו שלושים שנה סיים כל לימודו *u'chshe'higi'u shloshim shanah siyeim kol limudo*.
So it took 30 years of those of spending those two months
in חזרה *chazarah* to חזר *chazer* everything he knew. Okay. וכן עשה
בשלושים שנים אחרונים *ve'chen asah bi'shloshim shanim acharonim*. So for the first
30 years of his life he went through all his learning once,
and the second 30 years he went through all his learning the
second time. I don't exactly get how it works because he didn't
start learning at the age of zero and whatever, but okay fine.
Anyway, ומהדורא קמא היינו שלושים שנים ראשונים ומהדורא בתרא היינו שלושים שנים
אחרונים *u'Madura Kama hainu shloshim shanim rishonim u'Madura Basra hainu shloshim shanim
acharonim*. Very interesting. Okay. Back to the גמרא *Gemara*. והלכתא והלכה היא
יחלוקו *Ve'hilchasa ve'halacha hi yachloku*. They have equal leans and you divide
it. מיתיבי *Meisivei*, I'll ask you on this, לשבח קרקעות כיצד הרי
שמכר לחברו והשביח ובא בעל חוב וטרפה כשהוא גובה גובה את הקרן
מנכסים משועבדים והשבח מנכסים בני חורין *le'shevach karka'os keitzad harei she'machar le'chavero
ve'hishbiach u'ba ba'al chov u'terafah keshe'hu goveh goveh es ha'keren mi'nechasim meshubadim
ve'hashevach mi'nechasim bnei chorin*. Like we said before, Michael goes ahead and
Michael collects the loan, collects the קרקע *karka* from ישראל *Yisrael* there,
and he gets the קרקע *karka* and the שבח *shevach*, and presumably
we said why does he get the שבח *shevach*? Because I gave
him the future leans. But here's the problem. Not only did I
give Michael future leans, if we're going to assume I gave Michael
future leans, you know who else I gave future leans to? Who
else has leans against me to get paid off? ישראל *Yisrael*. ישראל
*Yisrael* here wants to be paid back for the investment. Well, for
also for the principle, right? He lost, and he's entitled to leans
for the principle. Like the שבח *shevach* he only gets from the
cash on hand. But the principle he can get paid up by
leans, right? So guess what? You know where his leans should go
for that principle? Not only on land I had when I sold
it to him, but if I'm also giving future leans to you,
I'm giving future leans to him. So his lean for the principle
apply to his שבח *shevach*. Do you understand? Only if you wrote
it in though. What? Only if you wrote it in, right? If
I wrote it in, right. Like so I collected, I had a
lean both on the קרקע *karka* and the שבח *shevach*, and he
can collect the principle from you and the שבח *shevach* from me?
He can collect, no, the principle. For collecting his principle, he has
leans, he has leans for collecting his principle. That was on land
I owed, I owned when I sold him the land, but on
property I would get in the future. You know what property I
would get in the future includes? The שבח *shevach* that he improved.
So he can collect his principle from the... So why does Michael
take away all the שבח *shevach*? He should have equal claims to
the שבח *shevach* according to this. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, ואי
איתא חצי שבח מיבעי ליה *ve'i isa chatzi shevach mibayei lei*. It
should only be half שבח *shevach*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, לא
מאי גובה נמי דקתני חצי שבח *lo mai goveh nami de'katani chatzi
shevach*. Fine, that's what we mean. Michael gets half the שבח *shevach*.
ישראל *Yisrael* gets to take back the other half as payment of
the principle. Okay. By the way, of course something that's a little
bit unclear here is why is the שבח *shevach* that ישראל *Yisrael*
made considered to be property that I came into possession of? Why
isn't it property that ישראל *Yisrael* came into possession of? So that's
not exactly explored, but anyway that's this sort of assumption of the
גמרא *Gemara*. So we will end with that with this fascinating question
of creating future leans, where clearly all of the evidence, although we
could say it's רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, all of the evidence and
the discussion at the end of the גמרא *Gemara* shows that we
assume that you can create future leans on the land, presumably for
the reason the רשב"ם *Rashbam* either because leans are an abstraction and
it's not like selling things, it's more an abstract right, or more
likely I think for what the רשב"ם *Rashbam* says, that the rabbis
allowed it in order to encourage like commerce and lending of money.